<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % allent SYSTEM "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/2007/w3centities-f.ent">
%allent;
]>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">> <info>
        <title>Short Attention Span Docbook Toolchain &ndash; Setup Guide</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>New Auburn Personal Computer Services LLC</orgname>
            <address>
                <city>Eau Claire</city>
                <street>611 Davis Avenue</street>
                <postcode>54703</postcode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <email>info@napcs.com</email>
        </author>
        <copyright>
            <year>2010</year>
            <holder>Brian P. Hogan</holder>
        </copyright>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>This short guide will walk you through everything you need to use this toolchain to
            author your own Docbook documents.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Package Contents</title>
            <para>This package contains all of the tools you need to start working with Docbook,
                including</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Docbook stylesheets</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An XML validation tool</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Saxon XSLT processor (version 6.5.3)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Apache FOP FO processor for making PDFs</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A copy of the Microsoft HHC program for building HTML Help files</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A sample project with an easy-to-use Ruby script to transform your
                        document into various formats</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Windows setup</title>
        <para>Windows users should use the installer <footnote>
                <para>Docbook setup for Windows:
                        <uri>http://www.napcsweb.com/files/docbook/docbook-setup.exe</uri></para>
            </footnote>which sets up the necessary files and also sets up the path.</para>
        <sidebar>
            <title>Manual installation </title>
            <para>The easiest way to use this package is to use the application installer, but if
                you need to do a manual install, you can download the docbook zip file from
                    <uri>http://www.napcsweb.com/files/docbook/docbook.zip</uri> and extract it to
                    <filename>c:\docbook</filename>. Next, you'll want to add this folder to your
                PATH. To do that, press <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Windows</keycap>
                    <keycap>Pause</keycap>
                </keycombo> to bring up the <application>System Properties</application> window.
                Select the <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> tab and then select the
                    <guibutton>Environmen Variables</guibutton> button. In the <guilabel>User
                    variables</guilabel> section, locate the Path variable and edit its contents.
                Append <code><![CDATA[;c:\docbook]]></code> to the end of the value. If there
                currently is no Path variable, create a new one called <emphasis>PATH</emphasis> and
                use <code><![CDATA[c:\docbook]]></code> for the value. Press
                    <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to commit these changes. Press
                    <guibutton>OK</guibutton> on the <application>System Properties</application>
                window to finish up.</para>
            <para>Open a new command prompt and type <command>SET</command>. The PATH variable now
                reflects the changes you made.</para>
        </sidebar>
        <sect2>
            <title>Installing a Java Runtime Environment</title>
            <para>Download the Java Runtime Environment from Sun <footnote>
                    <para>Java Runtime:
                        <uri>http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp</uri></para>
                </footnote> and get it installed on your system if you don't already have it. Once
                installed, open a new command prompt and type </para>
            <para><command>java -version</command></para>
            <para>You'll see something similar to this:</para>
            <screen><![CDATA[Java(TM) 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition (build 1.5.0_13-b05-237)
Java HotSpot(TM) Client VM (build 1.5.0_13-119, mixed mode, sharing)]]></screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Installing Ruby</title>
            <para>Download and install the One Click Ruby Installer<footnote>
                    <para>Ruby:
                            <uri><![CDATA[http://rubyforge.org/frs/?group_id=167&release_id=17128]]></uri></para>
                </footnote> and install it, accepting the defaults. To verify the installation, open
                a new command prompt and type</para>
            <para><command>ruby -v</command></para>
            <para>You'll see something like this:</para>
            <screen><![CDATA[ruby 1.8.6 (2007-03-13 patchlevel 0) [i386-mswin32]]]>
            </screen>
            <para>At this point, everything is installed and you're ready to begin. Test it out by
                creating a new project:</para>
            <para><command>generate book my_test_project with_sample</command></para>
            <screen><![CDATA[Creating docbook project...
 - my_test_project/xsl
 - my_test_project/images
 - my_test_project/images/src
 - my_test_project/cover
 - my_test_project/book.xml
 - my_test_project/chapter01.xml
 - my_test_project/Rakefile
 - my_test_project/template/xsl/pdf.xml
 - my_test_project/w3centities-f.ent
 Done]]></screen>
            <para>Now you have a simple sample project with a book file and a chapter. Convert this
                to a PDF to make sure everything works.</para>
            <para><command>cd my_test_project</command></para>
            <para><command>rake book.pdf</command></para>
            <para>You'll get a brand-new PDF of the sample book.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Mac OS X Setup</title>
        <para>Setup on Mac OS X 10.4 or above is quite easy. You have Java and Ruby already
            installed on the machine in most cases. All you need to do is download the files from
                <link xlink:href="http://www.napcs.com/products/docbook/"
                >http://www.napcs.com/products/docbook/</link> and extract to
                <filename>docbook</filename> in your home folder. Once extracted, you should have a
            list of files that resembles this in your <filename>~/docbook</filename> folder:</para>
        <screen><![CDATA[
            drwxr-xr-x  18 brianhogan  brianhogan   612B Apr  2 11:56 .
            drwx------+ 63 brianhogan  brianhogan   2.1K Apr  2 10:12 ..
            -rwxr-----   1 brianhogan  brianhogan    53K Apr  2 10:23 docbook.pdf
            -rwxr-----@  1 brianhogan  brianhogan   5.1K Apr  2 13:58 generate
            -rwxr-----   1 brianhogan  brianhogan   165B Apr  2 10:52 generate.bat
            drwxr-xr-x  35 brianhogan  brianhogan   1.2K Mar 31 10:15 jars
            drwxr-xr-x  11 brianhogan  brianhogan   374B Apr  3 21:05 template
            drwxr-xr-x  41 brianhogan  brianhogan   1.4K Mar 25 22:19 xsl]]>
            </screen>
        <note xml:id="note.permission.denied">
            <title>Permission Denied</title>
            <para>You may need to set the executable bit for the <filename>generate</filename>file
                so you can use it.</para>
            <para><command>chmod +x ~/docbook/generate</command></para>
        </note>
        <para>To create a new project, type</para>
        <para><command>~/docbook/generate book my_test_project with_sample</command></para>
        <para>This generates the project skeleton:</para>
        <screen><![CDATA[Creating docbook project...
 - my_test_project/xsl
 - my_test_project/images
 - my_test_project/images/src
 - my_test_project/cover
 - my_test_project/book.xml
 - my_test_project/chapter01.xml
 - my_test_project/Rakefile
 - my_test_project/xsl/pdf.xml
 - my_test_project/w3centities-f.ent
 Done]]></screen>
        <para>Now try generating a PDF.</para>
        <para><command>cd my_test_project</command></para>
        <para><command>rake book.pdf</command></para>
        <para>You'll get a brand-new PDF of the sample book.</para>
        <tip>
            <para>Add the <filename>docbook</filename> folder to your path to make the
                    <command>generate</command> command available without having to specify the full
                path. Modify your <filename>.bash_profile</filename> to change the path.</para>
        </tip>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>The Project Generator</title>
        <para>You've already seen how to generate a new book, but the generator is a bit more
            flexible.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Creating books</title>
            <para><command><![CDATA[generate book my_book sample]]></command> generates a new book
                with some sample content so you can see how you might construct your book. It also
                generates a sample external chapter file as an example of how you would split your
                book into multiple files.</para>
            <para><command><![CDATA[generate book my_book]]></command> generates a
                    <filename>book.xml</filename> file, a <filename>chapter01.xml</filename> file,
                and a PDF XSLT customization layer file, as well as the directory structure. This
                sets you up to start your book from scratch.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Chapters</title>
            <para>You can generate chapters as well so you don't have to remember what exactly goes
                into the chapter template.</para>
            <para><command><![CDATA[generate chapter chapter02]]></command> generates a
                    <filename>chapter02.xml</filename> file in your current directory.</para>
            <para><command><![CDATA[generate chapter chapter2/some_stuff]]></command> generates a
                    <filename>some_stuff.xml</filename> file in a <filename>chapter2</filename>
                folder within your current directory.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Articles</title>
            <para>An article is just like a book, except it doesn't have chapters. It's ideal for
                simple projects where you don't need the complex structure of a book. The document
                you're reading is marked up as a Docbook article.</para>
            <para><command><![CDATA[generate article foo]]></command> creates a new article called
                    <filename>article.xml</filename> in the <filename>foo</filename> subfolder of
                your current folder.</para>
            <screen><![CDATA[ - foo/images
 - foo/xsl
 - foo/xsl/pdf.xml
 - foo/Rakefile
 - foo/w3centities-f.ent
 - foo/article.xml]]>
            </screen>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Writing your First Book</title>
        <para>Your sample project contains the following files:</para>
        <screen><![CDATA[Creating docbook project...
 - my_test_project/xsl
 - my_test_project/images
 - my_test_project/images/src
 - my_test_project/cover
 - my_test_project/book.xml
 - my_test_project/chapter01.xml
 - my_test_project/Rakefile
 - my_test_project/w3centities-f.ent
 - my_test_project/xsl/pdf.xml
 Done]]></screen>
        <para><filename>xsl/</filename> contains <token>XSLT Customization Layers</token> for the
            various types of outputs. By default, the <filename>Rake task</filename> only uses a
            customization layer for the PDF output. A customization layer is simply a way for you to
            define your own style properties for your output. The customization layer imports the
            original Docbook XSLT file, and then you redefine your own transformations.</para>
        <para><filename>images/</filename> will contain any images you plan to reference in your
            document. It's a good idea to organize this by chapter.</para>
        <para><filename>cover/</filename> holds the cover for your book. Put a file called <filename>cover.pdf</filename> file there and you can use a special task to prepend the cover file to your book.</para>
        <para><filename>book.xml</filename> is a sample starter template that shows you how to
            compose a simple book. You can build this into a PDF right away, and you can modify it
            and use it as the basis for your book, or just leave it around as an example.</para>
        <para><filename>chapter01.xml</filename> is an example chapter for a book. It's included
            within <filename>book.xml</filename> so you can see how you might break apart a book
            into multiple files.</para>
        <para><filename>Rakefile</filename> is the script used to transform your document into an
            actual publication. See <xref linkend="sec.content.generation"/> to see how that
            works.</para>
        <para><filename>xsl/pdf.xml</filename> is the aforementioned customization layer for the PDF
            output. This is the only supported customization layer at this time. Look at the
                <filename>make</filename> to see how to add your own for other files. Additional
            defaults are coming in future releases.</para>
        <para>Open up the <filename>book.xml</filename> file and modify its contents to write your
            book. Then render a new output, as discussed in <xref linkend="sec.content.generation"
            />.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec.content.generation">
        <title>Generating Output from Docbook</title>
        <para>There are several output options available with Docbook. This package provides easy
            access to the most popular transformation methods</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>PDF and RTF documents</title>
            <para>Generating a PDF or an RTF document is a two-step process. The XML document needs
                to be processed and transformed into an XML-FO document which is ready for print.
                Then it needs to be converted into either RTF or PDF by another process. This
                package uses Apache FOP to handle this step. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Using Rake to build a book</title>
            <para>When you generate a new project with <command>new_book</command> you get a
                    <filename>Rakefile</filename> script written in the Ruby programming language.
                Ruby's a powerful language that's easy to learn and modify. That's the main reason
                it's used in this project. The other reason is that the script works on all
                platforms, whereas traditional makefiles work on Linux-based operating systems only.
                A Rakefile defines a script for use with the Rake utility popular in the Ruby
                community.</para>
            <para>The Rakefile doesn't include much. It actually includes another file that does all
                the work, and provides a variable used to locate the rest of the build chain
                files.</para>
            <sect3 xml:id="sec.Path.to.the.Build.Chain">
                <title>Path to the Build Chain</title>
                <para>When you generate a project, the generator will put the absolute path to the
                    Docbook build chain in your Rakefile. However, you can override this by setting
                    an environment variable. On Linux or Mac OS, this would be:</para>
                <programlisting>export SHORT_ATTENTION_SPAN_DOCBOOK_PATH=/usr/local/docbook             </programlisting>
                <para>On Windows, you'd do</para>
                <programlisting>SET SHORT_ATTENTION_SPAN_DOCBOOK_PATH=c:/docbook</programlisting>
                <para>Or you would add the Environment variable permanently through the the Control
                    Panel, or alternatively, use the Windows installer for the Short Attention Span
                    Docbook.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 xml:id="sec.Building">
                <title>Building</title>
                <para> By default, this script can generate HTML, PDF, and RTF outputs. Windows
                    users can also use it to generate Windows Help (CHM) documents if they have the
                        <filename>hhc.exe</filename> file from the HTML Help Workshop installed on
                    their system.</para>
                <para>The build script is easy to use. You simply specify the name of the input file
                    you want to use and the format you want to generate. To make things simple, the
                    script uses a file naming convention that matches your original docbook xml
                    file. </para>
                <para>For example, if you have a file called <filename>book.xml</filename>, you'd be
                    able to do the following transformations:</para>
                <para><command>rake book.html</command> to generate an HTML file of your
                    book.</para>
                <para><command>rake book.rtf</command> to generate an RTF file of your book.</para>
                <para><command>rake book.pdf</command> to generate a PDF file of your book.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Validation</title>
            <para>By default, the script calls out to the Docbook website to validate your file
                against the RelaxNG schema definition file. Sometimes you may want to work offline
                or you just know you're that awesome and don't need to validate. The script takes a
                    <command>VALIDATE=false</command> option that skips the validation step.</para>
            <para><command>rake pdf VALIDATE=false</command></para>
            <para>If you have problems with your document, you may get unexpected results, so use
                this with caution.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec.Additional.Customizations">
        <title>Additional Customizations</title>
        <para>I'm constantly updating the build chain to add additional features that I and others
            need to publish content.</para>
        <sect2 xml:id="sec.Drafts">
            <title>Drafts</title>
            <para>As you're writing, you may want to inform your readers and reviewers that you are
                in Draft mode. </para>
            <para><command>rake pdf DRAFT=true</command></para>
            <para>This turns on a background overlay and enables display of any remark tags in your
                document.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="sec.Covers">
            <title>Covers</title>
            <para>Create a book cover in your favorite graphics program, export it as a PDF called
                    <filename>cover.pdf</filename> and place it in your project folder. Run the
                command</para>
            <para><command>rake add_cover</command></para>
            <para>This will create the file <filename>book_with_cover.pdf</filename>. </para>
            <tip xml:id="tip.this.task.will.build.the.pdf.of.the.book.if.it.doesn't.exist.">
                <title>Automatic Building</title>
                <para>This task will build the PDF of the book if it doesn't exist.</para>
            </tip>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="sec.Preprocessing">
            <title>Preprocessing</title>
            <para>If you need to perform some work before building your book, you can define a
                    <methodname>:preprocess</methodname> task in your project's
                    <filename>Rakefile</filename>.</para>
            <para>To make things easier, several environment variables are available to you in your
                task.</para>
            <para>
                <table frame="none">
                    <title>Preprocessor variables</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Variable</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>ENV["SOURCE_FILENAME"]</entry>
                                <entry>The name of the source XML document (book.xml)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>ENV["TEMP_FILENAME"]</entry>
                                <entry>The temporary XML file created by the build chain. It's
                                    copied from the source file so you can preprocess it and not
                                    alter your original file.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>ENV["OUTPUT_FILENAME"]</entry>
                                <entry>The name of the output file. (book.pdf)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>ENV["FORMAT"]</entry>
                                <entry>The format. "pdf", "html", "rtf", "epub"</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>So, you can preprocess your document easily.</para>
            <programlisting language="ruby"><![CDATA[task :preprocess do
  `xmllint #{ENV["TEMP_FILENAME"]}`
end]]></programlisting>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="sec.Postprocessing">
          <title>Postprocessing</title>
          <para>Postprocessing works exactly the same way. You have access to the same environment variables as the preprocessor task. You can use this to automatically add the cover to the book, for example, by calling the <methodname>add_cover</methodname> task.</para>
          <programlisting language="ruby" linenumbering="none"><![CDATA[task :postprocess do
  Rake::Task["add_cover"].invoke if ENV["FORMAT"] == "pdf"
end]]></programlisting>
        <para>When you run <command>rake book.pdf</command>, you'll automatically get the cover attached to the book.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="sec.Forcing.a.Build">
          <title>Forcing a Build</title>
          <para>If you change a chapter file but not the book.xml file, the Rake task may not work as it hasn't detected a change in the file. This is just how Rake works, but you can force things to work by either deleting your existing PDF file or "touching" the <filename>book.xml</filename>file. If you're making a book called <filename>book.pdf</filename> you can use the command <command>rake build</command> which will <emphasis>always</emphasis> build, no matter what.</para>
             
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Licensing</title>
        <para>The software contained herein is subject to various licensing agreements.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Saxon 6</title>
            <screen><![CDATA[SAXON: Conditions of Use

Saxon
-----------

The contents of the downloaded file (saxon.zip), with the exception of the AElfred parser (see below), are subject to the Mozilla Public License Version 1.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/

Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under the License.

The Original Code of SAXON comprises all those components which are not explicitly attributed to other parties. It does not include the AElfred parser, which is redistributed under the licence described below.

The Initial Developer of the Original Code was Michael Kay. Individual modules identified as being created by James Clark, David Megginson, or John Cowan include separate IPR notices. All Rights Reserved.

Until January 2001 Michael Kay worked for International Computers Limited (ICL, now part of Fujitsu), and from February 2001 to January 2004 he worked for Software AG. These two companies both sponsored the development of Saxon and authorised its release under this license, but are not themselves parties to the license. Michael Kay now runs his own company, Saxonica, which has taken over all responsibility for Saxon development and support.

For reasons of continuity, the icl.com domain name is retained in package names and namespace URIs with the tacit consent of ICL, but this should not be taken to imply any ongoing ICL involvement.

If you produce a product that includes or requires SAXON, please refer to it as "The SAXON XSLT Processor from Michael Kay", and include the URL of the home page, which is at http://saxon.sourceforge.net/.

There is no guarantee of technical support, though I am usually able to answer enquiries within a few days. Please subscribe to the mailing list available at http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/saxon-help and raise any enquiries there. Also check the Saxon project pages on sourceforge for details of known errors; all bugs are listed there as soon as I have sufficient evidence to describe the nature of the problem.

AElfred
------------
Included in the Saxon distribution is a modified version of the AElfred XML parser originally developed by David Megginson at Microstar (no longer in existence). I have taken the relevant part of David Brownell's AElfred2 distribution, repackaged it, and fixed a few bugs. All changes are clearly documented in the source code.

This is distributed under the terms of Microstar's terms and conditions, which are as follows:
	

AElfred, Version 1.2
Microstar's Java-Based XML Parser
Copyright (c) 1997, 1998 by Microstar Software Ltd.
Home Page: http://www.microstar.com/XML/

AElfred is free for both commercial and non-commercial use and redistribution, provided that Microstar's copyright and disclaimer are retained intact. You are free to modify AElfred for your own use and to redistribute AElfred with your modifications, provided that the modifications are clearly documented.

DISCLAIMER

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose. Please use it AT YOUR OWN RISK.
	

David Brownell added the following statement:

/*
 * Copyright (c) 1999-2000 by David Brownell.  All Rights Reserved.
 *
 * This program is open source software; you may use, copy, modify, and
 * redistribute it under the terms of the LICENSE with which it was
 * originally distributed.
 *
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * LICENSE for more details.
 */

The version included with Saxon is David Brownell's code of 26 Feb 2000, modified as follows:

    * Changed the package name to com.icl.saxon.aelfred to prevent any accidental confusion with the original Microstar code or with David Brownell's version.
    * Fixed several bugs: (1) a bug in namespace handling (where an attribute xxx:name precedes the xmlns:xxx declaration) (2) poor diagnostics when end of file occurs prematurely
    * Subsetting the code to include only the XML non-validating parser and SAX driver, with appropriate changes to the setFeature() and getFeature() methods.
    * Some further changes made by David Brownell up to June 2001 have been incorporated.

Michael H. Kay
Saxonica Limited
22 June 2005]]></screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Apache FOP</title>
            <screen><![CDATA[                                 Apache License
                           Version 2.0, January 2004
                        http://www.apache.org/licenses/

   TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR USE, REPRODUCTION, AND DISTRIBUTION

   1. Definitions.

      "License" shall mean the terms and conditions for use, reproduction,
      and distribution as defined by Sections 1 through 9 of this document.

      "Licensor" shall mean the copyright owner or entity authorized by
      the copyright owner that is granting the License.

      "Legal Entity" shall mean the union of the acting entity and all
      other entities that control, are controlled by, or are under common
      control with that entity. For the purposes of this definition,
      "control" means (i) the power, direct or indirect, to cause the
      direction or management of such entity, whether by contract or
      otherwise, or (ii) ownership of fifty percent (50%) or more of the
      outstanding shares, or (iii) beneficial ownership of such entity.

      "You" (or "Your") shall mean an individual or Legal Entity
      exercising permissions granted by this License.

      "Source" form shall mean the preferred form for making modifications,
      including but not limited to software source code, documentation
      source, and configuration files.

      "Object" form shall mean any form resulting from mechanical
      transformation or translation of a Source form, including but
      not limited to compiled object code, generated documentation,
      and conversions to other media types.

      "Work" shall mean the work of authorship, whether in Source or
      Object form, made available under the License, as indicated by a
      copyright notice that is included in or attached to the work
      (an example is provided in the Appendix below).

      "Derivative Works" shall mean any work, whether in Source or Object
      form, that is based on (or derived from) the Work and for which the
      editorial revisions, annotations, elaborations, or other modifications
      represent, as a whole, an original work of authorship. For the purposes
      of this License, Derivative Works shall not include works that remain
      separable from, or merely link (or bind by name) to the interfaces of,
      the Work and Derivative Works thereof.

      "Contribution" shall mean any work of authorship, including
      the original version of the Work and any modifications or additions
      to that Work or Derivative Works thereof, that is intentionally
      submitted to Licensor for inclusion in the Work by the copyright owner
      or by an individual or Legal Entity authorized to submit on behalf of
      the copyright owner. For the purposes of this definition, "submitted"
      means any form of electronic, verbal, or written communication sent
      to the Licensor or its representatives, including but not limited to
      communication on electronic mailing lists, source code control systems,
      and issue tracking systems that are managed by, or on behalf of, the
      Licensor for the purpose of discussing and improving the Work, but
      excluding communication that is conspicuously marked or otherwise
      designated in writing by the copyright owner as "Not a Contribution."

      "Contributor" shall mean Licensor and any individual or Legal Entity
      on behalf of whom a Contribution has been received by Licensor and
      subsequently incorporated within the Work.

   2. Grant of Copyright License. Subject to the terms and conditions of
      this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual,
      worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable
      copyright license to reproduce, prepare Derivative Works of,
      publicly display, publicly perform, sublicense, and distribute the
      Work and such Derivative Works in Source or Object form.

   3. Grant of Patent License. Subject to the terms and conditions of
      this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual,
      worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable
      (except as stated in this section) patent license to make, have made,
      use, offer to sell, sell, import, and otherwise transfer the Work,
      where such license applies only to those patent claims licensable
      by such Contributor that are necessarily infringed by their
      Contribution(s) alone or by combination of their Contribution(s)
      with the Work to which such Contribution(s) was submitted. If You
      institute patent litigation against any entity (including a
      cross-claim or counterclaim in a lawsuit) alleging that the Work
      or a Contribution incorporated within the Work constitutes direct
      or contributory patent infringement, then any patent licenses
      granted to You under this License for that Work shall terminate
      as of the date such litigation is filed.

   4. Redistribution. You may reproduce and distribute copies of the
      Work or Derivative Works thereof in any medium, with or without
      modifications, and in Source or Object form, provided that You
      meet the following conditions:

      (a) You must give any other recipients of the Work or
          Derivative Works a copy of this License; and

      (b) You must cause any modified files to carry prominent notices
          stating that You changed the files; and

      (c) You must retain, in the Source form of any Derivative Works
          that You distribute, all copyright, patent, trademark, and
          attribution notices from the Source form of the Work,
          excluding those notices that do not pertain to any part of
          the Derivative Works; and

      (d) If the Work includes a "NOTICE" text file as part of its
          distribution, then any Derivative Works that You distribute must
          include a readable copy of the attribution notices contained
          within such NOTICE file, excluding those notices that do not
          pertain to any part of the Derivative Works, in at least one
          of the following places: within a NOTICE text file distributed
          as part of the Derivative Works; within the Source form or
          documentation, if provided along with the Derivative Works; or,
          within a display generated by the Derivative Works, if and
          wherever such third-party notices normally appear. The contents
          of the NOTICE file are for informational purposes only and
          do not modify the License. You may add Your own attribution
          notices within Derivative Works that You distribute, alongside
          or as an addendum to the NOTICE text from the Work, provided
          that such additional attribution notices cannot be construed
          as modifying the License.

      You may add Your own copyright statement to Your modifications and
      may provide additional or different license terms and conditions
      for use, reproduction, or distribution of Your modifications, or
      for any such Derivative Works as a whole, provided Your use,
      reproduction, and distribution of the Work otherwise complies with
      the conditions stated in this License.

   5. Submission of Contributions. Unless You explicitly state otherwise,
      any Contribution intentionally submitted for inclusion in the Work
      by You to the Licensor shall be under the terms and conditions of
      this License, without any additional terms or conditions.
      Notwithstanding the above, nothing herein shall supersede or modify
      the terms of any separate license agreement you may have executed
      with Licensor regarding such Contributions.

   6. Trademarks. This License does not grant permission to use the trade
      names, trademarks, service marks, or product names of the Licensor,
      except as required for reasonable and customary use in describing the
      origin of the Work and reproducing the content of the NOTICE file.

   7. Disclaimer of Warranty. Unless required by applicable law or
      agreed to in writing, Licensor provides the Work (and each
      Contributor provides its Contributions) on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
      implied, including, without limitation, any warranties or conditions
      of TITLE, NON-INFRINGEMENT, MERCHANTABILITY, or FITNESS FOR A
      PARTICULAR PURPOSE. You are solely responsible for determining the
      appropriateness of using or redistributing the Work and assume any
      risks associated with Your exercise of permissions under this License.

   8. Limitation of Liability. In no event and under no legal theory,
      whether in tort (including negligence), contract, or otherwise,
      unless required by applicable law (such as deliberate and grossly
      negligent acts) or agreed to in writing, shall any Contributor be
      liable to You for damages, including any direct, indirect, special,
      incidental, or consequential damages of any character arising as a
      result of this License or out of the use or inability to use the
      Work (including but not limited to damages for loss of goodwill,
      work stoppage, computer failure or malfunction, or any and all
      other commercial damages or losses), even if such Contributor
      has been advised of the possibility of such damages.

   9. Accepting Warranty or Additional Liability. While redistributing
      the Work or Derivative Works thereof, You may choose to offer,
      and charge a fee for, acceptance of support, warranty, indemnity,
      or other liability obligations and/or rights consistent with this
      License. However, in accepting such obligations, You may act only
      on Your own behalf and on Your sole responsibility, not on behalf
      of any other Contributor, and only if You agree to indemnify,
      defend, and hold each Contributor harmless for any liability
      incurred by, or claims asserted against, such Contributor by reason
      of your accepting any such warranty or additional liability.

   END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS

   APPENDIX: How to apply the Apache License to your work.

      To apply the Apache License to your work, attach the following
      boilerplate notice, with the fields enclosed by brackets "[]"
      replaced with your own identifying information. (Don't include
      the brackets!)  The text should be enclosed in the appropriate
      comment syntax for the file format. We also recommend that a
      file or class name and description of purpose be included on the
      same "printed page" as the copyright notice for easier
      identification within third-party archives.

   Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.]]>
                
                
            </screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Xerces</title>
            <screen><![CDATA[Apache License
Version 2.0, January 2004
http://www.apache.org/licenses/

TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR USE, REPRODUCTION, AND DISTRIBUTION

1. Definitions.

"License" shall mean the terms and conditions for use, reproduction,
and distribution as defined by Sections 1 through 9 of this document.

"Licensor" shall mean the copyright owner or entity authorized by
the copyright owner that is granting the License.

"Legal Entity" shall mean the union of the acting entity and all
other entities that control, are controlled by, or are under common
control with that entity. For the purposes of this definition,
"control" means (i) the power, direct or indirect, to cause the
direction or management of such entity, whether by contract or
otherwise, or (ii) ownership of fifty percent (50%) or more of the
outstanding shares, or (iii) beneficial ownership of such entity.

"You" (or "Your") shall mean an individual or Legal Entity
exercising permissions granted by this License.

"Source" form shall mean the preferred form for making modifications,
including but not limited to software source code, documentation
source, and configuration files.

"Object" form shall mean any form resulting from mechanical
transformation or translation of a Source form, including but
not limited to compiled object code, generated documentation,
and conversions to other media types.

"Work" shall mean the work of authorship, whether in Source or
Object form, made available under the License, as indicated by a
copyright notice that is included in or attached to the work
(an example is provided in the Appendix below).

"Derivative Works" shall mean any work, whether in Source or Object
form, that is based on (or derived from) the Work and for which the
editorial revisions, annotations, elaborations, or other modifications
represent, as a whole, an original work of authorship. For the purposes
of this License, Derivative Works shall not include works that remain
separable from, or merely link (or bind by name) to the interfaces of,
the Work and Derivative Works thereof.

"Contribution" shall mean any work of authorship, including
the original version of the Work and any modifications or additions
to that Work or Derivative Works thereof, that is intentionally
submitted to Licensor for inclusion in the Work by the copyright owner
or by an individual or Legal Entity authorized to submit on behalf of
the copyright owner. For the purposes of this definition, "submitted"
means any form of electronic, verbal, or written communication sent
to the Licensor or its representatives, including but not limited to
communication on electronic mailing lists, source code control systems,
and issue tracking systems that are managed by, or on behalf of, the
Licensor for the purpose of discussing and improving the Work, but
excluding communication that is conspicuously marked or otherwise
designated in writing by the copyright owner as "Not a Contribution."

"Contributor" shall mean Licensor and any individual or Legal Entity
on behalf of whom a Contribution has been received by Licensor and
subsequently incorporated within the Work.

2. Grant of Copyright License. Subject to the terms and conditions of
this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual,
worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable
copyright license to reproduce, prepare Derivative Works of,
publicly display, publicly perform, sublicense, and distribute the
Work and such Derivative Works in Source or Object form.

3. Grant of Patent License. Subject to the terms and conditions of
this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual,
worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable
(except as stated in this section) patent license to make, have made,
use, offer to sell, sell, import, and otherwise transfer the Work,
where such license applies only to those patent claims licensable
by such Contributor that are necessarily infringed by their
Contribution(s) alone or by combination of their Contribution(s)
with the Work to which such Contribution(s) was submitted. If You
institute patent litigation against any entity (including a
cross-claim or counterclaim in a lawsuit) alleging that the Work
or a Contribution incorporated within the Work constitutes direct
or contributory patent infringement, then any patent licenses
granted to You under this License for that Work shall terminate
as of the date such litigation is filed.

4. Redistribution. You may reproduce and distribute copies of the
Work or Derivative Works thereof in any medium, with or without
modifications, and in Source or Object form, provided that You
meet the following conditions:

(a) You must give any other recipients of the Work or
Derivative Works a copy of this License; and

(b) You must cause any modified files to carry prominent notices
stating that You changed the files; and

(c) You must retain, in the Source form of any Derivative Works
that You distribute, all copyright, patent, trademark, and
attribution notices from the Source form of the Work,
excluding those notices that do not pertain to any part of
the Derivative Works; and

(d) If the Work includes a "NOTICE" text file as part of its
distribution, then any Derivative Works that You distribute must
include a readable copy of the attribution notices contained
within such NOTICE file, excluding those notices that do not
pertain to any part of the Derivative Works, in at least one
of the following places: within a NOTICE text file distributed
as part of the Derivative Works; within the Source form or
documentation, if provided along with the Derivative Works; or,
within a display generated by the Derivative Works, if and
wherever such third-party notices normally appear. The contents
of the NOTICE file are for informational purposes only and
do not modify the License. You may add Your own attribution
notices within Derivative Works that You distribute, alongside
or as an addendum to the NOTICE text from the Work, provided
that such additional attribution notices cannot be construed
as modifying the License.

You may add Your own copyright statement to Your modifications and
may provide additional or different license terms and conditions
for use, reproduction, or distribution of Your modifications, or
for any such Derivative Works as a whole, provided Your use,
reproduction, and distribution of the Work otherwise complies with
the conditions stated in this License.

5. Submission of Contributions. Unless You explicitly state otherwise,
any Contribution intentionally submitted for inclusion in the Work
by You to the Licensor shall be under the terms and conditions of
this License, without any additional terms or conditions.
Notwithstanding the above, nothing herein shall supersede or modify
the terms of any separate license agreement you may have executed
with Licensor regarding such Contributions.

6. Trademarks. This License does not grant permission to use the trade
names, trademarks, service marks, or product names of the Licensor,
except as required for reasonable and customary use in describing the
origin of the Work and reproducing the content of the NOTICE file.

7. Disclaimer of Warranty. Unless required by applicable law or
agreed to in writing, Licensor provides the Work (and each
Contributor provides its Contributions) on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
implied, including, without limitation, any warranties or conditions
of TITLE, NON-INFRINGEMENT, MERCHANTABILITY, or FITNESS FOR A
PARTICULAR PURPOSE. You are solely responsible for determining the
appropriateness of using or redistributing the Work and assume any
risks associated with Your exercise of permissions under this License.

8. Limitation of Liability. In no event and under no legal theory,
whether in tort (including negligence), contract, or otherwise,
unless required by applicable law (such as deliberate and grossly
negligent acts) or agreed to in writing, shall any Contributor be
liable to You for damages, including any direct, indirect, special,
incidental, or consequential damages of any character arising as a
result of this License or out of the use or inability to use the
Work (including but not limited to damages for loss of goodwill,
work stoppage, computer failure or malfunction, or any and all
other commercial damages or losses), even if such Contributor
has been advised of the possibility of such damages.

9. Accepting Warranty or Additional Liability. While redistributing
the Work or Derivative Works thereof, You may choose to offer,
and charge a fee for, acceptance of support, warranty, indemnity,
or other liability obligations and/or rights consistent with this
License. However, in accepting such obligations, You may act only
on Your own behalf and on Your sole responsibility, not on behalf
of any other Contributor, and only if You agree to indemnify,
defend, and hold each Contributor harmless for any liability
incurred by, or claims asserted against, such Contributor by reason
of your accepting any such warranty or additional liability.

END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS

APPENDIX: How to apply the Apache License to your work.

To apply the Apache License to your work, attach the following
boilerplate notice, with the fields enclosed by brackets "[]"
replaced with your own identifying information. (Don't include
the brackets!)  The text should be enclosed in the appropriate
comment syntax for the file format. We also recommend that a
file or class name and description of purpose be included on the
same "printed page" as the copyright notice for easier
identification within third-party archives.

Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
                ]]>
            </screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Docbook Build Tools - make and new_book</title>
            <screen><![CDATA[Copyright (c) 2008 Brian Hogan

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
THE SOFTWARE.]]>
            </screen>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>
